Guide to the Klepetko Chapter, Society for Industrial Archaeology records 1985-2010
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Klepetko Chapter, Society for Industrial Archaeology records,
1985-2010
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 MHSlibrary@mt.gov
MC 389
Klepetko Chapter, Society for Industrial Archaeology
.8 linear feet
This collection consists of correspondence, financial records, organizational records, printed material, subject files, and miscellany created by the Klepetko Chapter of the Society of Industrial Archaeology, a Montana Chapter of an organization created to encourage the study, appreciation and preservation of the archaeological remains of the industrial and technological past.
Biographical Note
The Society for Industrial Archaeology was founded in October of 1971 in order to "bring together [those] who share a common interest in the archaeology of industry, engineering and technology." SIA's North American headquarters are at the Department of Social Sciences at Michigan Technological University in Houghton, Michigan. Montana's SIA chapter is named after Frank Klepetko, metallurgist and designer of Montana's two largest smelters - the Washoe Reduction Works in Anaconda, and the Boston and Montana Smelter in Great Falls. The Klepetko Chapter was established on February 22nd, 1986; it was the first SIA chapter west of the Mississippi. Among the officers elected at this inaugural meeting were President Mark Fiege, Vice President Fred Quivik, Secretary/Treasurer Dale Martin, Program Coordinator Mary McCormick, and Newsletter Editor Arthur Dolman. Since its inception, the Klepetko Chapter has had a consistent membership of around 50, produces a semi-annual newsletter, and visits historically significant industrial sites around the state at least once a year. Both the national organization and the state chapter also offer process tours of operating industrial facilities like sawmills, hydroelectric plants, gold mines and mills, oil refineries, and sugar beet processing plants. The Montana Chapter is dedicated to documenting, preserving, and interpreting historical industrial sites and artifacts.
This collection consists of correspondence (1985-2010); financial records (1985-2009), which include some yearly financial reports; organizational records, including membership and longevity lists (1985-2009); printed material (1986-2004), consisting primary of master newsletters and "as printed" versions; subject files (1986-2007), dealing primarily with the Klepetko Chapter's Fall and Spring field trips and tours; and miscellany, which includes several photos that were used in newsletters and flyers.
Arranged by series.
Collection is open for research
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Industrial Archaeology.
Industrial buildings--History.
Industrial equipment--History.
Helena, Mont.
Butte, Mont.
Neihart, Mont.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence
  - General (correspondents include: Gene Munson, Fred Quivik, Mark Fiege, and Sandy Norman), 1986-1990 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - General (correspondents include: Mark Baumler, Brian Shovers, Kerry Newcomer, and Fred Quivik), 1995-1998 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - General (correspondents include: Brian Shovers, Kerry Newcomer, and John Staicer), 1999-2000 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - General (correspondents include: Brian Shovers, Kerry Newcomer, Kate Hampton, Judy Bohrnsen, Thomas K. Reilly, and Fred Quivik), 2001-2004 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Financial Records
  - Annual reports, 1996-2010 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Financial reports, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Organizational Records
  - Klepetko Chapter Bylaws and Membership lists, 1985-2009 (Box-folder 1/7)
- Printed Material
  - Master Letterhead, n.d. (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Newsletters, 1986-2004 (Box-folder 2/1-2)
- Subject Files
  - Klepetko Chapter, 1986-1994 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - "SIA, Butte and Anaconda Revisited", 1997-2005 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - "Butte Fall Tour", 1989 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - "Klepetko Spring Tour, Neihart", 2000 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - "SIA, Fall Tour", 2003 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - "SIA Fieldtrips", 2006-2007 (Box-folder 2/8)
- Miscellany
  - Photos and reports used in newsletters (Box-folder 2/9)